The Last of the Deliverers

by POUL ANDERSON

In this persuasive picture of a future American society not quite like any other so far prophesied, Mr. Anderson is at his near-Sbatdan best in demonstrating that ideological opponents may be, at the same time, both right and both wrong.

When I was nine years old, we still had a crazy man living in our town. He was very old, almost a hundred I suppose, and all his kin were dead. But in those days every town still had a few people who did not belong to any family.

Uncle Jim was wrong in the head, but harmless. He cobbled for us. His shop was in the front room of his house, always prim and neat, and when you stood there among the good smells of leather and oil, you could see his living room beyond. He did not have many books, but shelf after shelf was loaded with tall bright sheafs cased in plastic— old as himself, and as cracked and yellow with their age. He called them his magazines, and if we children were good he sometimes let us look at the pictures in them, but we had to be very careful. After he was dead I had a chance to read the texts, which didn't make sense. Nobody would worry about the things the people in those magazines made such a fuss over. He also had a big antique television set, though why he kept it when there was nothing to receive but official calls and the town had a perfectly good set for them, I don’t know. But he was crazy.

Every morning his long stiff figure went for a walk down Main Street. The Trees there were mostly elms, grown tall enough to overshadow it and speckle the pavement with cool bright sunflecks. Uncle Jim was always dressed in his ancient clothes, no matter how hot the day, and summer in Ohio can get plenty hot. He wore frayed white shirts with scratchy, choky collars, and long trousers and a clumsy kind of jacket, and narrow shoes that pinched his feet. It was ugly, but he kept it painfully clean. We children, being young and therefore cruel, thought at first that because we never saw him unclothed he must be hiding some awful deformity, and teased him about it. But my aunt’s brother John made us stop, and uncle Jim never held it against us. He even trusted to give us candy he had made himself, till the town dentist complained; then all of us had solemn talks with our fathers and found out that sugar rots the teeth.

Finally we decided that Uncle Jim—we called him that, without saying on which side he was anyone’s uncle, because he wasn't really—wore all those clothes as a sort of background for his button that said win with willard, He told me once, when I asked, that Willard had been the last Republican President of the United States and a very great man who tried to avert disaster but was too late because the people were already far gone in sloth and decadence. That was a big lading for a nine-year-old head, and I still don’t really understand it, except that once the towns did not govern themselves and the country was divided between two big groups who were not even clans but who more or less took turns furnishing a President; and the President was not an umpire between towns and states, but ran everything.

Uncle Jim used to creak down Main Street past Townhall and the sunpower plant, then turn at the fountain and go by my father’s great-uncle Conrad’s house to the edge of town where the fields and Trees rolled to the blue rim of the world. At the airport he would turn and come back by Joseph Arakelian’s, where he always looked in at the hand looms and sneered with disgust and talked about automatic machinery; though what he had against the looms I don’t know, because Joseph’s weavery was famous. He also made harsh remarks about our ratty little airport and the town’s half-dozen flitters. That wasn’t fair: we had a very good airport, surfaced with concrete blocks ripped out of the old highway, and there were enough flitters for all our longer trips. You’d never get more than six groups going anywhere at any one time in a town this size.

But I wanted to tell about the Communist.

This was in the spring. The snow had melted and the ground begun to dry and our farmers were out planting. The rest of our town bustled with preparations for the Fete, cooking and baking, oh such a smell as filled the air, women trading recipes from porch to porch, artisans hammering and sawing and welding, the washlines afire with Sunday-best clothes taken out of winter chests, lovers hand in hand whispering of the festivals to come. Red and Bob and Stinky and I were playing marbles by the airport. It used to be mumbletypeg, but some of the kids flipped their knives into Trees and the Elders made a rule that no kid could carry a knife unless a grownup was with him.

So it was a fair sweet morning, the sky a dizzy-high arch of blue, sunlight bouncing off puffy white clouds and down to the earth, and the first pale whisper of green had been breathed across the hills. Dust leaped where our marbles hit, a small wind blew up from the south and slid across my skin and rumpled my hair, the world and the season and we were young.

We were about to quit, fetch our guns and take into the woods after rabbit, when a shadow fell across us and we saw Uncle Jim and my mothercousin Andy. Uncle Jim wore a long coat above all his other clothes, and still shivered as he leaned on his cane, and the shrunken hands were blue with cold. Andy wore a kilt, for the pockets, and sandals. He was our town engineer, a stocky man of forty, but once in the prehistoric past before I was born he had been on an expedition to Mars, and this made him a hero for us kids. We never understood why he was not a swaggering corsair. He owned three thousand books at least, more than twice the average in our town. He spent a lot of time with Uncle Jim too, and I didn’t know why. Now I see that he was trying to learn about the past from him, not the dead past mummified in the history books but the people who had once been alive.

The old man looked down at us and said: “You boys aren’t wearing a stitch. You’ll catch your death of cold.” He had a high, thin voice, but it was steady. In all the years alone, he must have learned how to be firm with himself.

"Oh, nonsense,” said Andy. “I’ll bet it’s sixty in the sun.”

“We was going after rabbits,” I said importantly, “I’ll bring mine to your place and your wife can make us a stew.” Like all children, I spent as much time with kinfolk as I did with my orthoparents, but I favored Andy’s home. His wife was a wonderful cook, his oldest son was better than most on the guitar, and his daughter's chess was just about my speed, neither too good nor too bad.

I’d won most of the marbles this game, so now I gave them back. “When I was a boy,” said Uncle Jim, “we played for keeps.”

“What happened after the best shooter had won all the marbles in town?" asked Stinky. “It’s hard work making a good marble, Uncle Jim. I can’t hardly replace all I lose anyway.”

“You could have bought some more,” he told him. “There were stores where you could buy anything."

“But who made all those marbles?”

“There were factories—”

Imagine that! Big grown men spending their lives making colored glass balls!

We were almost ready to leave when the Communist showed up. We saw him as he rounded the clump of Trees at the north quarter-section, which was pasture that year. He was on the Middleton road, and dust scuffed up from his bare feet.

A stranger in town is always big news, and we kids started running to meet him till Andy recalled us with a sharp word and reminded us that he was entitled to proper courtesy. So we waited, with our eyes bugging out, till he reached us.

But this was a woebegone stranger. He was tall and thin, like Uncle Jim, but his cape hung in rags about a narrow chest where you could count all the ribs, and under a bald dome of a head was a dirty white beard down to his waist. He walked heavily, leaning on a staff, heavy as Time, and even then I sensed the loneliness like a weight on his thin shoulders.

Andy stepped forward and bowed. “Greetings and welcome, Freeborn,” he said. “I am Andrew Jackson Welles, town engineer, and on behalf of the Folks I bid you stay, rest, and refresh yourself.” He didn’t just rattle the words off as he would for someone he knew, but declaimed them with great care.

Uncle Jim smiled then, a smile like thawing after a nine year’s winter, for this man was as old as himself and born in the same forgotten world. He trod forth and held out his hand. “Hello, sir,” he said. “My name is Robbins. Pleased to meet you.” They didn’t have very good manners in his day.

"Thank you, Comrade Welles, Comrade Robbins,” said the stranger. His smile was lost somewhere in that tangled mold of whiskers. “I’m Harry Miller.”

“Comrade?" Uncle Jim spoke it slowly, like a word out of a nightmare, and his hand crept back again. “What do you mean?”

The newcome wanderer straightened and looked at us in a way that frightened me. "I meant what I said,” he answered. “I don’t make any bones about it. Harry Miller, of the Communist Party of the United States of America!”

Uncle Jim sucked in a long breath. "But—” he stammered, “but I thought ... at the very least, I thought all you rats were dead.”

“Now hold on,” said Andy. “Your pardon, Freeborn Miller. Our friend isn’t, uh, isn’t quite himself. Don’t take it personally, I beg you.”

There was a grimness in Miller’s chuckle. “Oh, I don’t mind. I’ve been called worse than that.”

“And deserved it!” I had never seen Uncle Jim angry before. His face got red and he stamped his cane in the dust. “Andy, this, this man is a traitor. D’you hear? He’s a foreign agent!”

“You mean you come clear from Russia?” murmured Andy, and we boys clustered near with our ears stiff in the breeze, because a foreigner was a seldom sight.

“No,” said Miller. “No, I'm from Pittsburgh. Never been to Russia. Wouldn’t want to go. Too awful there—they had Communism once.”

“Didn’t know anybody was left in Pittsburgh," said Andy. “I was there last year with a salvage crew, after steel and copper, and we never saw anything but birds."

“A few. A few. My wife and I— But she died, and I couldn’t stay in that rotting empty shell of a city, so I went out on the road."

“And you can go back on the road,” snarled Uncle Jim.

“Now, please be quiet,” said Andy. “Come on into town, Freeborn Miller—Comrade Miller, if you prefer. May I invite you to stay with me?”

Uncle Jim grabbed Andy’s arm. He shook like a dead leaf in fall, under the heartless fall winds. “You can’t!” he shrieked. “Don’t you see, he’ll poison your minds, he’ll subvert you, we’ll end up slaves to him and his gang of bandits!"

“It seems you’ve been doing a little mind-poisoning of your own, Mister Robbins,” said Miller.

Uncle Jim stood for a moment, head bent to the ground, and the quick tears of an old man glimmered in his eyes. Then he lifted his face and pride rang in the words: “I am a Republican.”

“I thought so.” The Communist glanced around and nodded to himself. “Typical bourgeois pseudo-culture. Look at those men, each out on his own little tractor in his own field, hugging his own little selfishness to him.”

Andy scratched his head. “What are you talking about, Freeborn?” he asked. “Those are town machines. Who wants to be bothered with keeping his own tractor and plow and harvester?”

“Oh . . . you mean—” I could see a light of wonder in the Communist's eyes, and he half stretched out his hands. They were aged hands, I could see the bones just under the dried-out skin. “You mean you do work the land collectively?”

“Why, no. What on earth would be the point of that?” replied Andy, “A man’s entitled to what he raises himself, isn’t he?”

“So the land, which should be the property of all the people, is parceled among those kulaks!” flared Miller.

“How in hell’s name can land be anybody’s property? It’s . . . it’s land! You can’t put forty acres in your pocket and walk off with them.”

Andy took a long breath. “You must have been pretty well cut off from things in Pittsburgh— ate the ancient canned stuff, didn’t you? I thought so, It’s easy enough to explain. Look, that section out there is being planted in corn by my mothercousin Glenn. It’s his corn, that he swaps for whatever else he needs. But next year, to conserve the soil, it’ll be put in alfalfa, and my sisterson Willy takes care of it then. As for garden truck and fruit, most of us raise our own, just to get outdoors each day."

The light faded in our visitor, “It doesn’t make sense,” said Miller, and I could hear how tired he was. It must have been a long hike from Pittsburgh, living off handouts from gypsies and the Lone Farmers.

“I quite agree,” said Uncle Jim with a stiff kind of smile. “In my father’s day—” He closed his mouth. I knew his father had died in Korea, in some war when he was just a baby, and Uncle Jim had been left to keep the memory and the sad barren pride of it. I remembered my history, which Freeborn Levinsohn taught in our town because he knew it best, and a shiver crept in my skin. A Communist! Why, they had killed and tortured Americans . . . only this was a faded rag of a man, he couldn’t kill a puppy. It was very odd.

We started toward Townhall, People saw us and began to crowd around, staring and whispering as much as decorum allowed. I strutted with Red and Bob and Stinky, right next to the stranger, the real live Communist, under the eyes of all the other kids.

We passed Joseph’s weavery, and his family and apprentices came out to join the goggle eyes. Miller spat in the street. “I imagine those people are hired!” he said.

“You don’t expect them to work for nothing, do you?” asked Andy,

“They should work for the common good.”

“But they do. Every time somebody needs a garment or a blanket, Joseph gets his boys together and they make one. You can buy better stuff from him than most women can make at home.”

“I knew it. The bourgeois exploiter—”

“I only wish that were the case,” said Uncle Jim, tight-lipped.

“You would,” snapped Miller.

"But it isn’t- People don’t have any drive these days. No spirit of competition. No desire to improve their living standard. No . . . they buy what they need, and wear it while it lasts—and it’s made to last damn near forever.” Uncle Jim waved his cane in the air. “I tell you, Andy, the country’s gone to hell. The economy is stagnant. Business has become a bunch of miserable little shops and people making for themselves what they used to buy!”

“I think we’re pretty well fed and clothed and housed,” said Andy.

“But where’s your . . . your drive? Where’s the get-up-and-go, the hustling, that made America great? Look—your wife wears the same model of gown her mother wore. You use a flitter that was built in your father’s time. Don’t you want anything better?”

“Our machinery works well enough," said Andy. He spoke in a bored voice, this was an old argument to him while the Communist was new, I saw Miller’s tattered cape swirl into Si Johansen’s carpenter shop and followed.

Si was making a chest of drawers for George Hulme, who was getting married this spring. He put down his tools and answered politely,

“Yes . . , yes, Freeborn , . , sure, I work here. . . . Organize? What for? Social-like, you mean? But my apprentices got too damn much social life as it is. Every third day a holiday, damn near. . . No, they ain't oppressed. Hell, they’re my own kin! . . . But there ain’t any people who haven’t got good furniture. Not unless they’re lousy carpenters and too uppity to get help—”

“But the people all over the world!” screamed Miller. “Don’t you have any heart, man? What about the Mexican peons?”

Si Johansen shrugged. “What about them? If they want to run things different down there, it’s their own business.” He put away his electric sander and hollered to his apprentices that they could have the rest of the day off. They’d have taken it anyway, of course, but Si was a little bit bossy.

Andy got Miller out in the street again, and at Townhall the Mayor came in from the fields and received him. Since good weather was predicted for the whole week, we decided there was no hurry about the planting and we'd spend the afternoon welcoming our guest.

“Bunch of bums!” snorted Uncle Jim, “Your ancestors stuck by a job till it was finished.”

“This’ll get finished in time,” said the Mayor, like he was talking to a baby. “What’s the rush, Jim?”

“Rush? To get on with it—finish it and go on to something else. Better things for better living!”

"For the benefit of your exploiters,” cackled Miller. He stood on the Townhall steps like a starved and angry rooster,

“What exploiters?” The Mayor was as puzzled as me,

“The ... the big businessmen, the—”

“There aren’t any more businessmen,” said Uncle Jim, and a little more life seemed to trickle out of him as he admitted it. “Our shopkeepers . . . no. They only want to make a living. They've never heard of making a profit. They’re too lazy to expand,”

“Then why haven’t you got socialism?” Miller’s red eyes glared around as if looking for some hidden enemy. “It’s every family for itself. Where’s your solidarity?” “We get along pretty well with each other, Freeborn,” said the Mayor. “We got courts to settle any arguments.”

“But don’t you want to go on, to advance, to—”

"We got enough,” declared the Mayor, patting his belly. “I couldn’t eat any more than I do.”

“But you could wear more!" said Uncle Jim. He jittered on the steps, the poor crazy man, dancing before all our eyes like the puppets in a traveling show. "You could have your own car, a new model every year with beautiful chrome plate all over it, and new machines to lighten your labor, and—”

“—and to buy those shoddy things, meant only to wear out, you would have to slave your lives away for the capitalists," said Miller. “The People must produce for the People,”

Andy traded a glance with the Mayor. “Look, Freeborns,” he said gently, “you don’t seem to get the point. We don’t want all those gadgets. We have enough. It isn’t worthwhile scheming and working to get more than we have, not while there are girls to love in springtime and deer to hunt in the fall. And when we do work, we’d rather work for ourselves, not for somebody else, whether you call the somebody else a capitalist or the People. Now let’s go sit down and take it easy before lunch.”

Wedged between the legs of the Folks, I heard Si Johansen mutter to Joseph Arakelian: "I don’t get it. What would we do with all this machinery? If I had some damn machine to make furniture for me, what’d I do with my hands?” Joseph lifted his shoulders. “Beats me, Si, Personally, I’d go nuts watching two people wear the same identical pattern.”

“It might be kind of nice at that,” said Red to me. “Having a car like they show in Uncle Jim’s magazines.”

“Where’d you go in it?” asked Bob.

“Gee, I dunno. To Canada, maybe. But shucks, I can go to Canada any time I can talk my dad into borrowing a flitter.”

“Sure,” said Bob. “And if you’re going less than a hundred miles, you got a horse, haven’t you ? Who wants an old car?”

I wriggled through the crowd toward the Plaza, where the women were setting up outdoor tables and bringing food for a banquet. The crowd was so thick around our guest where he sat that I couldn’t get near, but Stinky and I skun up into the Plaza Tree, a huge gray oak, and crawled along a branch till we hung just above his head. It was a bare and liver-spotted head, wobbling on a thread of neck, but he darted it around and spoke shrill.

Andy and the Mayor sat near him, puffing their pipes, and Uncle Jim was there too. The Folks had let him in so they could watch the fireworks. That was perhaps a cruel and thoughtless thing to do, but how could we know? Uncle Jim had always been so peaceful, and we’d never had two crazy men in town.

“I was still young,” Comrade Miller was saying, “I was only a boy, and there were still telecasts. I remember how my mother cried, when we knew the Soviet Union was dissolved. On that night she made me swear to keep faith, and I have, I have, and now I’m going to show you the truth and not a pack of capitalist lies.”

“Whatever did happen to Russia?" wondered Ed Mulligan. He was the town psychiatrist, he’d trained at Menninger clear out in Kansas. “I never would have thought the Communists would let their people go free, not from what I’ve read of them.”

“The Communists were corrupted,” said Miller fiercely. "Filthy bourgeois lies and money.”

“Now that isn’t true,” said Uncle Jim, "They simply got corrupt and easygoing of their own accord. Any tyrant will. And so they didn’t foresee what changes the new technology would make, they blithely introduced it, and in the course of one generation their Iron Curtain rusted away. Nobody listened to them any more.”

“Pretty correct, Jim,” said Andy. He saw my face among the twigs, and winked at me, “There was some violence, it was more complicated than you think, but that’s essentially what happened. Trouble is, you can’t seem to realize that it happened in the USA also,” Miller shook his withered head. “Marx proved that technological advances mean inevitable progress toward socialism,” he said. “Oh, the cause has been set back, but the day is coming.”

“Why, maybe you’re right up to a point,” said Andy. “But you see, science and society went beyond that point. Maybe I can give you a simple explanation.”

“If you wish,” said Miller, grumpy-like.

“Well, I've studied the period. Technology made it possible for a few people and acres to feed the whole country, so there were millions of acres lying idle; you could buy them for peanuts. Meanwhile the cities were over-taxed, underrepresented, and choked by their own traffic. Along came the cheap sunpower unit and the high-capacity accumulator. Those made it possible for a man to supply most of his own wants, not work his heart out for someone else to pay the inflated prices demanded by an economy where every single business was subsidized or protected at the taxpayer’s expense. Also, by living in the new way, a man cut down his money income to the point where he had to pay almost no taxes—so he actually lived better on a shorter work week.

“More and more, people tended to drift out and settle in small country communities. They consumed less, so there was a great depression, and that drove still more people out to fend for themselves. By the time big business and organized labor realized what was happening and tried to get laws passed against what they called un-American practices, it was too late; nobody was interested. It all happened so gradually, you see . . . but it happened, and I think we’re happier now.”

“Ridiculous!” said Miller. "Capitalism went bankrupt, as Marx foresaw two hundred years ago, but its vicious influence was still so powerful that instead of advancing to collectivism you went back to being peasants.”

"Please,” said the Mayor. I could see he was annoyed, and thought that maybe peasants were somebody not Freeborn. “Uh, maybe we can pass the time with a little singing.”

Though he had no voice to speak of, courtesy demanded that Miller be asked to perform first. He stood up and quavered out something about a guy named Joe Hill. It had a nice tune, but even a nine-year-old like me knew it was lousy poetics. A childish a~b~c-b~ scheme of masculine rhymes and not a double metaphor anywhere. Besides, who cares what happened to some little tramp when there are hunting songs and epics about interplanetary explorers to make? I was glad when Andy took over and gave us some music with muscle in it.

Lunch was called, and I slipped down from the Tree and found a seat nearby. Comrade Miller and Uncle Jim glowered at each other across the table, but nothing was said till after the meal, a couple of hours later. People had kind of lost interest in the stranger as they learned he’d spent his life huddled in a dead city, and wandered off for the dancing and games. Andy hung around, not wanting to but because he was Miller’s host.

The Communist sighed and got up. "You’ve been nice to me,” he said.

“I thought we were all a bunch of capitalists,” sneered Uncle Jim.

"It’s man I’m interested in, wherever he is and whatever conditions he has to live under,” said Miller.

Uncle Jim lifted his voice with his cane: “Man! You claim to care for man, you who only killed and enslaved him?”

“Oh, come off it, Jim,” said Andy. “That was a long time ago. Who cares at this late date?”

“I do!” Uncle Jim started crying, but he looked at Miller and walked up to him, stiff-legged, hands clawed. “They killed my father! Men died by the tens of thousands —for an ideal! And you don’t care! The whole damn country has lost its guts!”

I stood under the Tree, one hand on the cool rough comfort of its bark. I was a little afraid, because I did not understand. Surely Andy, who had been sent by the United Townships Research Foundation all the long black way to Mars, just to gather knowledge, was no coward. Surely my father, a gentle man and full of laughter, did not lack guts. What was it we were supposed to want?

“Why, you bootlicking bellycrawling lackey,” yelled Miller, “it was you who gutted them! It was you who murdered working men, and roped their sons into your dummy unions, and , . . and , . . what about the Mexican peons?”

Andy tried to come between them. Miller’s staff clattered on his head. Andy stepped back, wiping the blood off, looking helpless, as the old crazy men howled at each other. He couldn’t use force—he might hurt them.

Perhaps, in that moment, he realized. “It’s all right, Freeborns,” he said quickly. "It’s all right. We’ll listen to you. Look, you can have a nice debate tonight, right in Townhall, and we’ll all come and—”

He was too late. Uncle Jim and Comrade Miller were already fighting, thin arms locked and dim eyes full of tears because they had no strength left to destroy what they hated. But I think, now, that the hate arose from a baffled love. They both loved us in a queer maimed fashion, and we did not care, we did not care.

Andy got some men together and separated the two and they were led off to different houses for a nap. But when Dr. Simmons looked in on Uncle Jim a few hours later, he was gone. The doctor hurried off to find the Communist, and he was gone too.

I only learned that afterward, since I went off to play tag and pom-pom-pullaway with the other kids down where the river flowed cool and dark. It was in the same river, next morning, that Constable Thompson found the Communist and the Republican. Nobody knew what had happened. They met under the Trees, alone, at dusk when bonfires were being lit and the Elders making merry around them and lovers stealing off into the woods. That’s all anybody knows. We gave them a nice funeral.

It was the talk of the town for a week, and in fact the whole state of Ohio heard about it, but then the talk died and the old crazy men were forgotten. That was the year the Brotherhood came into power in the north, and men worried what it could mean. The next spring they learned, and there was an alliance made and war went across the hills. For the Brotherhood gang, just as it had threatened, planted no Trees at all, and such evil cannot go unpunished.